翻译/压制/字幕制作：HAF半个水果
Hello everybody. So in this video I'll show you how I ran Linux on Microsoft Excel.
大家好。在这个视频中，我将向大家展示如何在Microsoft Excel上运行Linux
使用AI工具翻译，如有不准确的地方请在弹幕或评论区指正，谢谢！
翻译质量权威评价：原来25年就有小拉即用机翻糊弄人了
Microsoft Excel is a very powerful suit and you can do lots of things in it.
Microsoft Excel是一款功能非常强大的软件，你可以在其中完成许多任务
Accountants love it.
会计师们很喜欢它
Software engineering students despise it
软件工程专业的学生对它深恶痛绝
because universities hate their software engineering students
因为大学讨厌他们的软件工程专业学生
and force them to do Excel assignments.
还强迫他们做Excel作业
True story.
真事
But anyway, enthusiasts do all sorts of freaky stuff in Excel,
但不管怎样，爱好者们在Excel里总能玩出各种疯狂的花样
and this project is just an excuse for me to make a funny video.
而这个项目只是我为了拍个有趣的视频找的借口
Originally, NSG 650 made that thing,
最初，NSG650制作了这个东西
and he tweeted about it. I got pretty excited, so I contacted him about it,
他还在推特上发了相关内容。我对此感到非常兴奋，于是联系了他
and he then published the source code.
然后他公布了源代码
Unfortunately, upon closer inspection, I realized his version was pretty bare bones,
遗憾的是，经过仔细检查后，我发现他的版本相当简陋
only printing the output.
只有打印输出
And I thought it'd make a pretty lame video.
我还以为这视频会拍得很无聊
So ultimately, I decided to chip in and sort of finish the project for him, making it interactive.
最终，我决定插手帮忙，算是替他完成了这个项目，还让它具备了互动性
Took me a couple hours, but I'm pretty happy with how it turned out.
花了我几个小时，但对最终的效果相当满意
I don't want to take long. So, let's just see it in action.
我不想说太多。直接看实际操作吧
And then I'll explain how it works.
然后我会解释它是如何工作的
All right. So, to run it, it's simple enough. Just open the Excel spreadsheet.
好的。那么，运行它很简单。只需打开Excel电子表格即可
It's not an ordinary spreadsheet, as you can probably tell by the file name already.
这不是一份普通的电子表格，从文件名你大概就能看出来
It's a spreadsheet full of macros.
这是一张满是宏的电子表格
I can smell your fear. Don't worry, there is no macro virus in here.
我能闻到你恐惧的气息。别担心，这里没有宏病毒
These times are long over
那样的日子早已一去不复返
Though you should probably keep an eye out just in case.
不过以防万一，你最好还是留意一下
So, you open that file and wow,
好了，你打开文件，哇
this is Linux running in Microsoft Excel.
这是在Microsoft Excel中运行的Linux
Unbelievable. Let me make this a little
难以置信。让我把界面
more viewable by scaling the interface up.
放大一点，这样看起来更清楚
There we go. If the screen overflows, it just resets the A column.
好了。如果屏幕溢出，它就会重置A列
so this is the reason there isn't all that extra boot information at the beginning we used to have when it wasn't scaled up.
这就是为什么启动时没有看到所有那些额外引导信息了
The rules are simple. There are no rules. It's Linux.
规则很简单。没有规则。这就是Linux
But jokes aside, the entire A column is reserved for the terminal output.
玩笑归玩笑，整个A列是专门留给终端输出的
But where do you run the Linux commands? Good question.
但在哪里运行这些Linux命令呢？问得好
I reserved the C2 cell specifically for the terminal input.
我特意为终端输入保留了C2单元格
That's where you run them.
那就是你运行它们的地方
You can do all the terminal basics in that powershell.
你可以在那个PowerShell中完成所有终端基础操作
run the directory listing
列举目录
switch the directories
切换目录
create files
创建文件
even enter and exit Vim.
甚至可以进入和退出 Vim
The only critical mistake you can make is entering the insert mode in Vim.
在Vim中，唯一可能犯的致命错误就是进入插入模式
Naturally, you'd need to press escape to get back out
当然，你需要按Esc键才能返回
but there is so far no way to input that in the cell.
但目前还没有办法在单元格中输入这个
I mean, you can technically create magic sequences that translate to special keys
我是说，从技术上讲，你可以创建映射到特殊键的魔法序列
but I didn't bother to implement that.
但我懒得去实现
It's a simple switch case statement in the handler function.
这是处理函数中的一个简单switch case语句
But anyway, you can even run scripts,
但不管怎样，你甚至可以运行脚本
even though I kind of failed to do that,
尽管我在这方面有些失败了
I think, because I couldn't input the new line after the shebang.
我想，是因为我无法在单元格后面换行
So, it's still pretty raw.
所以，它还相当简陋
There are lots of things you can do,
有许多事情你可以做
but from here on out, it's just tedious work of implementing different magic sequences,
但从现在开始，就只剩下实现各种魔法序列的繁琐工作了
essentially converting input from an Excel cell to the Linux std in.
本质上将Excel单元格的输入转换为Linux的标准输入
Not a fan of tedious work.
不喜欢繁琐的工作
Anyway, let's just say I tried to run devil fetch even though it's a bash script and there is no bash here.
不管怎样，就说我试图运行devil fetch吧，尽管这是个bash脚本而这里根本没有bash环境
Hope dies last.
希望最后才会破灭
Spoiler, it did not work.
剧透一下，这没有用
And moreover, it crashed the macro a couple times I tried.
而且，我试了几次，它还导致宏崩溃了几次
I guess the coolest tedious thing you can implement is the ASI escape sequences support
我猜你能实现的最酷又繁琐的功能就是支持ASI转义序列
so that you could beautify the output.
这样你就可以美化输出结果
But again, it's pretty annoying to implement.
但话说回来，实现起来还是挺烦人的
So yeah, this is Linux running in Microsoft Excel.
没错，这就是在Microsoft Excel里运行的Linux
What's the catch?
有什么猫腻？
Well, you could consider it cheating because it's not Linux running in native Excel formulas.
嗯，你可以认为这是作弊，因为它并不是在原生Excel公式中运行的Linux
If you do want to implement Linux in pure Excel formulas,
如果你确实想在纯Excel公式中实现Linux
I'm so sorry for you, my friend.
我很抱歉无法实现，我的朋友
But be my guest. In reality, Linux is running in a separate library that's loaded into Excel
但请随意。实际上，Linux运行在一个独立的库中
via the VBA macro. Excel here basically acts as the IO interface.
该库通过VBA宏加载到Excel中。这里的Excel基本上充当了输入输出接口的角色
The library we're using is mini RV32
我们使用的库是mini RV32
which is the tiniest risk V emulator that fits inside a C header.
这是能塞进C语言头文件的最小RISC-V模拟器
I don't really want to go in depth into the technicalities neither of the VBA macro nor the library.
我既不想深入探讨VBA宏的技术细节，也不想讨论这个库的技术问题
I'll try to explain in simple terms.
我会尽量用简单的语言来解释
Basically, an emulator allows you to step tick by tick with a function.
基本上，模拟器允许你通过一个函数逐步执行每个时钟周期
And each tick there is an event loop that's running.
每个时钟周期都有一个正在运行的事件循环
Every tick, essentially a moment in time you choose
每一个时刻，本质上是你选择的一个时间点
you get to send input into the emulator and receive output from it.
你可以向模拟器发送输入并接收其输出
The VBA macro runs 2 to the power of 17 ticks in the emulator at the very beginning
VBA宏在模拟器中最初运行时以及每次接收到输入时，会运行2的17次方个时钟周期
and every time input is received.
I just picked that number because I think number 17 is cool.
我选那个数字只是因为我觉得17很酷
And it was somewhat the golden middle between the macro freezing Excel entirely
这大致是在宏完全冻结Excel与给予模拟器足够时间
and having enough time for theemulator to run an average command and return the output from it.
运行平均命令并返回输出之间的一个理想折中点
So that's how the VBA script works essentially
这就是VBA脚本的基本工作原理
the library is a little more tricky to explain in simple terms
用简单的语言来解释这个库有点复杂
but the event loop is located in it
但事件循环位于其中
and the CSR read and write functions are invoked every tick.
每个时钟周期都会调用CSR的读写函数
So we get to process input and send the output with the functions exported from the DLL.
因此我们可以处理输入并通过从DLL导出的函数发送输出
They're then imported and used accordingly in the VBA script.
随后它们被导入并在VBA脚本中相应使用
It's just an orchestra really.
这不过是个协调分工的过程
That's one of the more weird and satisfying projects I have worked on since the start of my channel.
这是我频道创立以来做过的最古怪又最令人满足的项目之一
I can't thank NSG650 enough for sharing the initial source code.
我无法充分感谢NSG650分享最初的源代码
This wouldn't have been possible without him.
但没有他，这一切都不可能实现
He's a cool guy. Check him out.
他是个很酷的家伙。去关注他吧
I'm going to leave both the source code and the compiled library along with a micro sheet in the description below
我将在下面的描述中同时提供源代码、编译好的库以及一份简要说明
so you can try it out for yourself.
这样你就可以亲自尝试一下
Tweet the coolest stuff you can execute in that spreadsheet at me
把你能在那个电子表格里执行的最酷的东西发推给我
I'm Andderman on Twitter.
我推特是endermanch
I'll retweet the craziest stuff you guys execute.
我会转发你们执行的那些最疯狂的事情
I believe collectively you can do much more than me in such a stripped down Linux version.
我相信在这个精简版的Linux系统中，你们集体能做的远比我一个人多
And I'm sorry if my voice is kind of annoying right now.
如果我现在的声音有点烦人，我很抱歉
I'm currently sick and my nose is stuffed.
我现在生病了，有点鼻塞
原标题：Running Linux in Microsoft Excel 原作者：Enderman
I'm trying my best to voice things over right now.
我正在尽力为当前的内容配音
原视频上传日期：2025年4月30日
Thanks for watching and take care.
感谢观看，保重
在 Youtube 上关注
翻译/压制/字幕制作：HAF半个水果
翻译质量权威评价：原来25年就有小拉即用机翻糊弄人了
向所有字幕制作及相关人员道一声辛苦了 (*ˊᗜˋ*)/ᵗᑋᵃᐢᵏ ᵞᵒᵘ*
感谢字幕组的默默耕耘，你们的每一行字都能让更多人能够跨越语言障碍，享受精彩的内容
字幕制作不易，喜欢的话支持一下我吧！